A Guide to the Dudley-Rexrode Collection, 1873-1998
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Duxley RExrode Collection1873-1998
Special Collections, James Madison University
SC 5039
3 boxes (1.5 linear feet)
Collection of personal papers and ledgers relating to the Dudley and Rexrode families. Included in this collection are the receipts, invoices, and tax documents of E.A. Dudley; ledgers from the practice and pharmacy of C.P. Rexrode; ledgers from the agricultural business of A.B. Dudley; family photographs; and documents from the Mossy Creek Presbyterian Church in Augusta County, Virginia.
: E.A. Dudley, M. Dudley Rexrode, C.P. Rexrode, A.B. Dudley, Agnes Rexrode, Alberta Dudley Brand
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Acquired at Public Auction in 2008
Provenance
The Estate of M. Dudley Rexrode
Biographical Information
The papers were acquired from the estate of Marshall Dudley Rexrode(1905-2006). Mr. Rexrode graduated from Bridgewater College and attended Virginia Tech. He was a prominent farmer and member of the community in Mt. Solon, Augusta County, Virginia. He was a charter member of the North River Ruritan Club and served as their treasurer for 45 years. Mr. Rexrode was an elder, deacon and chairman of the board of trustees for Mossy Creek Presbyterian Church (a historic church established in 1768 in Augusta County). Mr. Rexrode was also the secretary-treasurer of the Rockingham County Land Bank Association and assistant secretary-treasurer of Staunton Production Credit Association. He served on the Augusta County Planning Commission three times. Additionally, he was director and president of the Augusta County Farm Bureau Federation, as well as director and president of the Augusta County Petroleum Co-op. His work on various boards, social organizations and church related activities is evidence of his active community involvement. M. Dudley Rexrode was in possession of the papers of Dr. Charles P. Rexrode (his father) and Edward Alexander Dudley(his maternal grandfather), which were also acquired with this collection. Charles P. Rexrode, M.D. was a physician and pharmacist in Crab Bottom, Highland County, Virginia (now Blue Grass, VA). The Highland Recorder (a local newspaper) contains references to Dr. Rexrode treating patients and making house calls during times of emergency. Edward A. Dudley(1850-1927) was a prominent farmer and cattle raiser in Highland County and Augusta County, Virginia. Mr. Dudley was living in the Churchville area of Augusta County when he passed away in May 1927. Also included in this collection are photographs and correspondence relating to M. Dudley Rexrode’s Aunt, Alberta Dudley Brand. Mrs. Brand and her husband Dr. Louis Christian Brand were Presbyterian Missionaries in Japanese Korea from 1924-1938, during the time that Korea was occupied by Japan. Dr. Brand was a physician and third director of the Ellen-Lavine Graham Hospital (now the Kwangju Christian Hospital) in Kwangju, Korea, where he was devoted to the elimination of tuberculosis.
Scope and Content
The collection contains financial records of the Dudley-Rexrode family, including tax records, insurance records, and ledgers of family businesses, that included C.P. Rexrode's medical practice and A.B and E.A. Dudley's agricultural business. This collection also includes 139 family photographs (including photographs of the Dudley-Brand family in Korea in the 1930s). Additionally, there is a large collection of documents from the Mossy Creek Presbyterian Church, where M. Dudley Rexrode served as a Deacon and Elder. The content mainly deals with economic and religious life in the Shenandoah Valley during the late 19th and early 20th Century.
Arrangement
Items have been arranged chronologically and by creator.
The collection is arranged in 5 series:
I: The Papers of E.A. Dudley, 1876-1920
II: The Papers of C.P Rexrode, 1907-1925
III: The Papers of A.B. Dudley, 1915-1961
The Papers of M. Dudley Rexrode, 1963-2005
Miscellaneous, 1913-1985
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
“Attempted Suicide” Highland Recorder. 1903 December 18. p.3. Blair, Charles William. A History of Mossy Creek Presbyterian Church. Bridgewater Beacon Printing, Inc. Bridgewater, VA. 2000. “Edward A. Dudley” Staunton News Leader. 1927 May 31. p.4. “History” Kwangju Christian Hospital Website. Accessed 2012 Dec. 5. http://kch.or.kr/eng/history.html. “M.Dudley Rexrode” Daily News-Record. 2006 January 30. p.10. “Nonagenarian Rexrode is Ruritans’ Citizen of Year”. Daily News-Record. 1995 October 23. p.16 “Staunton Man Dies in Korea” Daily News-Record. 1938 March 2. p.8.
Contents List
- Papers of E.A. Dudley1876-1920
  - IOUs and Person to Person Tansactional Notes1884-1912 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Mutual Insurance Company (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Copy of Mutual Insuarnce Policy-, June 15, 1888
    - Payment Receipts, 1893, 1896 and 1897
  - Tax Payments, 1887-1912 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Commerical Invoices and Receipts, 1876-1915 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Land Deeds, 1873-1904 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspndence (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Letter fron Congressman Henry D. Flood, March 3, 1908
    - Letter concerns the "Blackleg" vaccine for cattle
    - Letter from J.P. Russel to E.A. Dudley- 1920 Sept. 15
    - Letter is in regards to cattle sales
    - Empty Envelope Addressed to E.A. Dudley
- Papers of C.P. Rexrode 1907-1925
  - Ledger, 1909-1913 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Ledger, 1912 (Box:folder 1:8)
  - Ledger, 1913 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Ledger, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Ledger, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Medical Examiner's Report, Life Insuarnce Co. of Pittsburgh (Box-folder 1:12)
  - C.P. Rexrode Correspondence, 1909-1913 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - Thank You Letter, 1916
    - Check-1917
      Made to Dr. Rexrode in 1917 for examination fees
    - Bank Receipt, 1924
    - Pamphlet-National Balsam Ointment, 1924
    - Bill from Bridgewater College, 1924
    - Card- Endocrine Preparations, 1924
    - Receipt for Neodyne, 1925
    - Receipt from automotive Dealer, 1925
  - C.P. and Agnes Recrode Receipts, 1907-1959 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Papers of A.B. Dudley 1915-1961
  - Ledger, 1915-1930 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Ledger, 121-1922 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Ledger, 1925-1927 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Ledger, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Financial Documents (Box:folder 2:5)
    - Check- 1916
    - Section 225 of the Code of VA
    - Note from E.P Harvey, 1917
- Papers of Dudley Rexrode 1936-2005
  - Diary (Box-folder 2:6)
    Inscribed "This book was give (sic) me by Mary Lee Long as guest prize at Polly Ann engagement party. 1936 May 29th." Diary desiged to cover five years, sparsely used in 1936. May have belonged to Alice of Agnes Rexrode.
  - Checkbook Stubs, 1936 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Notebook - Farm Operations, 1946 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Receipt - Pioneer Corn Co., 1962 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Ledger-Personal Finances (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Dudley/Rexrode Family Photographs, 4 Negatives; 104 Photos (Box:folder 3:1)
    - 4 Negatives
    - 15 VA Tech. talem ny M. Dudley Rexrode
    - 10 Agricultural Photos
    - 5 Taken at a mountain retreat, 1930s
    - 17 Photos of Agnes Rexrode (possible)
    - 5 Photos of Agnes and her Mother, Margaret
    - 5 Rexrode Family pictures from the 1930s
    - 5 Potentially Identifed Photos
    - 25 Unidentified Photographs
    - 3 Unidentified Group Photos
      Possibly at Mossy Creek Prsbyterian Church
    - 1 Christmas Greeting Photo
      Ernest M. Rexrode Family, 1969
    - Two Donkeys (1 Photo)
    - Young woman in cardboard frame- circa late 1920s
      Dean Studio, Harrisonburg, VA
  - Dr. Louis and Alberta Dudley Brand Photographs and Correspondence, 35 Photographs; 1 Postcard; 2 letters (Box-folder 3:2)
    Alberta Dudley Brand was the younger sister of Margaret Dudley Rexrode. Alberta and her husband, Dr. Louis Christian Brand, were Presbyterian missionaries in Korea from 1924-1938. Additionally, Dr. Brand was a physician 3rd directory of the Ellen-Lavine Graham Hospital in Kwangju
    - 7 Hand-colored photod of the Brand Children, Korea, 1927-1938
    - 10 Photos of Alice and Martha Brand, Korea, 1933-1938
    - 2 Photos of the "Kwangju Graduates" Korea, 1936
    - 1 Martha Brand and Jim Rodgers, Korea, Christmas 1993
    - 1 Alice Brand and "the elders babay" Korea
    - 5 Photos of Louis "Dudley" Brand, Korea 1934-1935
    - 4 Photos of Louis "Dudley" Brand, Virginia 1942
    - 1 Postcard, unused
      "The Summer resort of foreigner at Katsuma Peninsula (Korea)"
    - Letter from Alice, Kwangju, Korea, December 1935
    - Alberta Dudley Brand Letter, Korea
  - Newspaper Clippings and Funeral Memory Books (Box:folder 3:3)
    - Funeral Memory Books
      - Luther Charles Fultz, 1947
      - J. Wayne Fairburn, February 1993
      - Agnes Rxrode, October 1993
      - Maggie Elizabeth Props, 1995
      - Richard Craig Duedley, 1998
      - Luther Charles Fultz, 1947
    - Clipped Newspaper Obituaries
      - John H. Earhart
      - Mabel Rexrode, 1995 December 14
      - S. Newton Karicofe, 1996 September 10
      - Eark T. Swink, 1996 September 10
      - Clarence E. May, 1997 April 15
      - Kathleen C. McFall, 1997 December 7
      - Richard C. Dudley, 1998 May 23
      - Nancy R. Lewis, 1998 August 25
      - Garland Miller, 1998 September 7
      - Rudolph B. Alexander, 1999 June 6
      - William A Brooks, 1999 November 16
      - Francis Dudley, 2000 April 8
      - Hiram C. Arey, 2000 APril 30
      - Hiwana C. Crompton, 2000 May 4
      - Richard J. Hevener, 2000 June 12
      - Roy R. Smith, 200 November 28
      - Arthur V. Bartenslayer, 2002 August 11
      - William J. Moffett, Jr., 2002 August 10
      - Dr. John H. Guss, 2004 September 28
      - John A Horn, 2005 May 15
    - 2 Wedding Announcement
      - Charlotte Leww Reeves Graham
      - Betty Jean Simmons Young, 1950 February 10
    - 7 Local Interest Articles
      - Hightown Bank President Reminisces on 85th Birthday, May 1948
      - Mrs. Fred Whipple wind Creativity Award
      - Retiring Teachers Honored
      - Augusta Co. Farm Bureau
      - Mt Solon Mail Carrier Leaves Post
      - Churchville Bears, 1955 July 10
    - Ruchmond Times-Dispatch Section F, 1968 February 4
    - 4 "Dear Abby" and Letter to the Editor Clippings
    - 2 Miscellaneous Clippings
  - Mossy Creek Presbyterian Church Materials (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Handbook and Directory
    - Minutes of the Borad of Directors Meeting, 1968 December 16
    - United Presbyterian Church of the USA Staff Information
    - "Confessions of our Church" Manual
    - Board of Directors Resolution, 1960 June 12
    - Regarding Mrs. Georgia Williams Whisman's Property, 1970 October 10
    - From Mrs. George W. Whisman to Board of Directors, 1970 April 18
    - From the Borad of Directors to Mrs. Georgia Whisman
    - Mossy Creek Church Service Bulletin, 1992 April 16
    - M. Dudley Rexrode Trust and Will, 1993 April 2
    - Handwritten Instructions for Arranging Flowers
  - Mossy Creek, 200th Anniversary Celebrations, 1968 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Program
    - Script
    - Stage Directions
    - Draft of Article for Newspaper or Newsletter
  - Ruritan Club Publications (Box:folder 3:6)
    - North River Ruritan Club Handbook, 1998
    - Woodrow Wilson District Convention, 1995
- Miscelanneous1913-1985
  - Correspondences 1960s (Box-folder 3:7)
    Addressed to Joe and Ed, concerning the illness of Alice
  - Correspondence of Martha Rexrode (Box-folder 3:8)
    - "Flora Manor"- Parnassus VA Poem and Letter, 1947
    - Card, 1984
    - Card
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Farm Co Op News, 1970
    - Certificate of Incorporation, North River Telephone Co.
    - Disney Magic Kingdom Ticket Stubs
    - Handwriting Character Analysis
    - Beverly Manor Academy Final Exercises, 1913
    - Christmas Card
    - Thinking of You Card
    - Envelope Addressed to M. Dudley
    - Calling Card- Blanche A. Corrie
    - Postage Stamps, 3 cents
    - Postcard- Fort Matanzas
    - North River Augusta Fair and Horse Show, 1939
    - "Table Grace You Can See"
    - W-A Intestinal Antisepctic announcement
    - "Tested Light Conditioning Recipes
    - Envelope Addressed to Agnes Rexrode
    - Picture "Pals" (Girl and Puppy), 1925
    - Picture "Autumn", 1925